TAWSIF KHAN

519-503-4405 | t35khan@uwaterloo.ca | https://tawsifkhan.github.io/

Profile

An inquisitive analytics professional with a background in engineering and mathematics. Dedicated and passionate, enjoys research, mathematical analysis and solving problems that require critical thinking. Experienced programmer with a track record of creating tools, systems and data layers that make analytic functioning more efficient.

Work experience

Consultant, Financial Analytics 08/2017 - present

Aimia Inc., Toronto, Canada

- Perform in-depth research and analysis to derive insights and drive informed business decisions in the Amex and CIBC portfolios
- Develop profitable campaigns in a data-driven way with personalized offers that reduce churn and improve member engagement
- Build business reviews for partners and perform post-campaign analysis to derive key insights and actionable recommendations for future efforts

Client Analyst, Analytics 12/2015 - 07/2017

McKinsey PriceMetrix Co., Toronto, Canada

- Designed performance benchmarking models to help wealth management firms and advisors make fact based decisions
- Developed efficient automated systems to generate quantitative reports for financial advisors
- Communicated with Client Managers and brainstormed ideas for executive reviews of major wealth management firms in the North American industry
- Served Scotia Wealth Management, Desjardins, Odlum Brown and other wealth management firms as the lead analyst in executive reviews

Research Assistant, Dept. of Applied Mathematics 2013 – 2015

University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Canada

- Responsible for independent and collaborative research in the Control of Infinite dimensional Systems group
- Presented and critiqued concepts and results in regular research group meetings
- Published and presented research work in the American Control Conference

Teaching Assistant, Dept. of Engineering and Applied Science 2011 – 2015

University of Waterloo/North South University

- Communicated complex concepts with students during tutorials of 50+ enrollment
- Evaluated exam scripts, developed marking rubrics, managed undergraduate markers
- Individually organized tutorial sessions for students beyond regular duties
- Received exceptional reviews from students and instructors

Education

MMath in Applied Mathematics 2013 – 2015

University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Canada

BS in Electrical Engineering 2008 – 2013

North South University, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Skills

Functional

Python, R, SQL, SAS Data preparation, collection, and cleansing Statistical modelling Insights presentations

Industry Experience

Credit Cards & Loyalty Marketing Campaigns Wealth Management Financial Markets

Champion Traffic Jam Toronto Hackathon, City of Toronto 2015

Analyzed the unreliability of Toronto road network using Toronto Transit data and located the 50 most unreliable
locations of the city which require attention to control traffic congestion. Python and R were used for the
project. Team received a prize money of \$5000.

3 Minute Thesis Finalist University of Waterloo 2015

- Represented Faculty of Mathematics in the 2015 University of Waterloo 3MT finals
- Explained the breadth and significance of my thesis to a non-specialist audience
- URL https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u34rAAUxuPE

Summa Cum Laude North South University 2013

Daily Star Certificate of Excellence GCE O and A Level 2008

Projects

Aimia Inc.

- Lead a team of 13 in Aimia's 2018 Data Philanthropy event. Built a data cleaning and segmentation tool using R, and lead 5 other objective streams to deliver a full suite of operational improvement solution to Rainbow Railroad, a Canadian charitable organization
- Introduced bootstrapping to the analytics team for significance testing and built a tool to carry out the tests
- Build a data layer using Amex billing cycle data for more efficient analytic works

McKinsey PriceMetrix Co.

- Developed an automated system using SQL to compute a comprehensive list of performance measures for a given client benchmarked against the industry
- Replicated an in-house software using SQL and VBA for the analytics team which allows more customizability

Advanced Analytics

- Implemented a TFIDF driven gradient boosting regression model for Kaggle Mercari Price Suggestion Challange
- Used RShiny to create a visualization tool for the global terrorism database
- Implemented a Random Forest Classifier to determine the Cuisine using ingredients as feature
- Independently developed a game, Get The Odds, on MATLAB using Min-Max Algorithm
- Collaboratively developed an Image Pixel Classifier on MATLAB using neural networks

TJTO Hackathon

Collaboratively analyzed Toronto transit data to locate unreliable spots in Toronto's road network

MMath Thesis

Developed software using MATLAB for optimal state estimation of a dispersive wave equation (Tags: Kalman filter, Navier-Stokes, Optimal Control, Finite Element Method)

Bloomberg Hackathon

 Implemented an algorithm using MATLAB and an interface using Python to make intelligent buyingselling orders of stock in the UW Bloomberg Algorithmic Trading competition

BS. Thesis

Numerically solved 2D Navier-Stokes equation using Fortran to simulate blood flow.

Publications

Computation of the optimal sensor location for the estimation of an 1-D linear dispersive wave equation American Control Conference

http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7172162/?reload=true